Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the science fiction radio show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is Bill Vernon.
And Daryl Lane.
Science Fiction Chronicle is a major
science fiction and fantasy news magazine
distributed by Algol Press, which appears
monthly.
Its publisher is Andrew Porter, who for
most of his life has been a science
fiction fan.
Porter told us how I discovered science
fiction. It's a story familiar to most of
us.
My brother was reading SF first.
He's five years older than I am.
So when he was fifteen, I was ten.
I just started picking it up from him.
And uh
he still reads SF, but obviously I have
gone much further, much deeper into the
subject than he would have ever dreamed
of.
Porter went on to produce several fan
publications, and he started Al Gol
Magazine. Algol was later named Starship,
which is still a viable magazine.
Porter founded Algol Press when his
ambitions grew.
Science fiction chronicle is another one
of the productions of Algol Press.
We asked him who else is involved in
running Al Gol Press.
When I started the wanted to start
publishing like chat books and books and
stuff like that, I adopted the name Algol
Press
from Al Gol Magazine.
But it's not really uh
it just you know sort of like the name I
press, and if I do chat books or or books
or something, I mean I did one I did one
book, really.
I did the book of Elson, which is a real,
you know, hardcover and a trade paperback.
But people think it's I work for this vast
Algol Press.
And of course, also the appearance of
Starship and Chronicle, like wow, typeset
and Starship has or at least had four
colour covers.
Well, he's got this vast organization
behind him. He's not a fan at all, they
say.
Pasting stuff up in my living room.
After having published several fanzines,
Porter started Science Fiction Chronicle.
It was the magazine he had always dreamed
of doing.
So for years I carried on my business
card. You have a business card and
impresses people and costs five bucks or
five thousand.
I had a thing called SF Chronicle listed
in there, you know, which was just a
title.
And it was like the newsing I was wanted
to do it finally in 1979.
I started as a news section in LGL,
which that time it became Starship by
then, changed the title more hardcore SF
title.
And um
it started out
with um
you know, getting subscriptions.
So in other words, I actually started it
with several hundred subscriptions.
And it was just thing then the the way I
want to do it, like typeset and nicely
laid out and
stuff like that.
Science fiction Chronicle just had its
fourth birthday.
It's a rarity for a science fiction news
magazine to have survived for so long.
Through the years, various people have
started up news zines, and they've all
folded.
They've all gone away, they've all stopped
publishing, and people got tired, or they
got tired of losing money or something.
And it didn't, it's still here.
I mean it's not
it's I don't think it's making money yet,
but it's uh it's uh it's at the break-even
point,
which is always nice.
Advertising is increasing, and now the
recession's ending.
Things are starting to take off.
Why would a fan devote his life to
producing a news magazine such as Science
Fiction Chronicle?
Especially since it doesn't net him much
profit. Porter told us his reasons.
I've always loved science fiction.
I mean, I could probably make a lot more
money publishing a magazine with a lot of
naked people in it, right?
Or, you know, or
um something motorcycles or you know,
Hell's Angels official newsletter or
something like that.
You know, if you don't buy this newsletter
will kill you.
One of those things, I don't know.
But uh
I just love science fiction.
I've always loved science fiction, and uh
if I can make my living doing something in
science fiction, that's great.
Porter also gets a kick out of producing
science fiction chronicle.
Um the kick really is getting up when I
feel like it and working until when I feel
like it, and not having a boss to yell at
me and say you screwed up, and or I
screwed up and you're gonna take the blame
because I'm your boss.
We'll have more on our next show with
publisher Andrew Porter.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
And here are your hosts.
This is Darrell Lane. And
Bill Vernon. Al
Gol Press is a one-man operation which
publishes the magazine Starship, an
occasional book in the monthly trade
newspaper, Science Fiction Chronicle.
Andrew Porter of Brooklyn is the one-man
operator. He handles all aspects of the
business, from subscriptions to
advertising, from editorializing to
arranging the printing.
Recently we spoke with Porter and we asked
him to describe a typical work day.
And um
I hit a whole bunch of stuff in one stop
on the subway.
Um there's my
commercial bank from my accounts, uh, you
know, Starship and SF Chronicle and stuff,
and then two doors away there's the my
personal savings bank.
Across the street is the New York office
of of the printer I use.
And I can go in there and use their tie
line and co-op
the printer out in Pennsylvania and find
out how stuff's doing.
Or I can deliver stuff that has to be, you
know, they have a pouch system overnight.
There's a stationary store near there I
use, and uh my post office box is up there
in Grand Central Station,
and the place where where I have uh
pictures developed
and all that and you know then I I come
back home and uh
I'll do other stuff at night.
I like to work late at night, very quiet.
Um I have the TV going as a background
noise. I watch uh
I watch Johnny Carson and then David
Letterman comes on, and then after that
there's a very good news program called
News Overnight and NBC.
Which is very tongue in cheek.
They do a lot not ready for primetime news
and other strange things.
And then uh if I'm really working straight
through, there's two issues two episodes
of uh Mary Tyler Moore come on.
Followed by an episode of Bob Newhart.
And by that time it's four in the morning,
and uh then I Love Lucy Rerun comes out.
Usually I can't stand that and all so I
just turn off and go to speech.
Or I'll knock off the door earlier and
then read.
The April 1983 issue of Science Fiction
Chronicle had some startling headlines.
Cherry spin red to wed collaborate.
Dahl pays fifty million dollars for New
American Library.
The New England Science Fiction
Association acquired Sherriton Boston.
These turned out to be
fictitious. They were an April Fool's
joke. Porter told us about it.
I asked people's permissions to do that.
I asked Don Warren's permission to use
that do that story, and I asked Charlie's
permission and I asked Spinrads, and I I
arranged uh this uh sort of a matchmaker
thing and saying, Well, who would you like
to get married to?
You know, and Sherry didn't mind Spin Red
and Spinwriter didn't mind Cherry.
And I ran those stories, and a
heck of a lot of people believe those
stories. I understand that various writers
were calling other writers out and reading
the issues over the phone and stuff.
And people who knew Spinrad knew he was
planning to move right in the air and
said, You slide devil, you're gonna move
to Oak Lahoma, not Los Angeles.
And um
if it's set in tight, people believe it.
Porter promised there will be a special
treat to appear in the April 1984 issue of
science fiction chronicle.
For next April, I have two ideas I'm gonna
use, and this one was kind of funny and
and and humorous, like the thing with the
uh New England Science Fiction Association
buying the shirt in Boston, you know.
And I have two ideas I'm gonna use one is
gonna be either
I won't tell you what they are, the
specific ideas, but one will either be
kind of interesting and humorous, or the
other it might be horrifying, and I think
will scare the hell out of a lot of
people, and it won't be humorous,
but it's gonna be possible.
But it's gonna scare a lot of people, and
I think it might anger a lot of people
too. But it'll be interesting, it'll be a
hoax.
More with Andrew Porter on our next show.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Perme and Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the science fiction radio show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is
Darrell Lane.
There are several professional science
fiction magazines still in operation.
Amazing stories, analog, asimov science
fiction, and fantasy and science fiction
of the present-day survivors.
Scores of professional magazines have come
and gone over the past sixty years.
There's a niche in science fiction,
though, which is filled by a handful of
magazines published sporadically, like the
professional monthly magazines, these semi
pro scenes comprise stories, articles, and
interviews. One such magazine is Starship,
subtitled the magazine about science
fiction. We talked recently with
Starship's publisher, Andrew Porter of
Algol Press, who also produces the news
magazine, Science Fiction Chronicle.
Porter told us that running such a
magazine is certainly affected by the
state of the economy.
And then 1972 went to twice a year, and
then in seventy-four I think went to three
times a year.
And then when the recession hit
I consider this whole these last quote,
two unquote recessions we've had
as one big recession.
And then what happened to Starship
happened across the field, or just across
publishing period.
Um within the period of um a an issue or
so. Um bookstore sales dropped by half to
two-thirds.
Um people just decided, you know, it was
more important to pay their money or buy
food or something like that.
And advertising dropped off a lot too.
Um the best store I had I think was 79.
Uh had one issue with 40 pages of
advertising with a 90 some odd page issue.
And that just dropped tremendously during
the recession.
Uh all the stuff dried up.
And uh it reached the point instead of
making a small profit,
it was making a small loss.
So the more issues I published, the more
money it would lose.
So what was the point?
So I just basically ended up suspending
publication for for slightly over a year.
In order for Starship to survive, Porter
finds that he must constantly seek ways to
lower production costs.
Here he tells us of one ploy.
The weird thing about Starship is
um
Chronicle, I write most of it, and
obviously I'm not paying myself
for writing all this stuff.
Starship is all stuff where you have to
pay for it, except the letters and the
editorial.
Um
the printing costs are much higher than
Chronicle because uh you've got um uh four
colour cover on Chrome coat.
Um the um print run is larger, the overall
magazine.
Um mailing costs are higher
because it weighs more.
Um
so what I did the last issue, I went from
a four colour cover to a two colour cover.
And it I think it it looks good, it
doesn't look like I've seen other people
do two colors and they do well.
The artwork is up is in blue and then the
pipe is in black, right?
I used them to like that.
So not having a four color cover, I saved
about
three hundred dollars in the cost of
colour separations and another four or
five hundred dollars in the printing.
Porter told us of still another tactic for
saving on the cost of production.
Remember, these strategies allow him to
continue producing starship.
This new issue, I'm not gonna have a
cover.
It's gonna be a self-cover, but it's gonna
be the outside form for the printing is
gonna be two colors.
So it'll have an effective two-color
cover.
But not having that cover
and just putting it sort of the on the
run. Actually, what I might do is I'll
write run the outside form on slick paper.
So it'll be like eight pages of slip paper
in the front and eight pages in the back,
and then uncoded the rest of it.
And that'll save the cost of having a
chrome court cover and stuff.
That'll save nine hundred dollars.
How many copies you have to sell to make
that nine hundred dollars?
So
and also it's it's gone twice either now.
And um
so it's basically the difference between
doing something that'll make a small
profit and something that'll lose.
And you can't publish something that's
gonna lose money.
This has been the science fiction radio
show production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the science fiction radio show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is Darrell Lane.
And Bill Vernon.
Artis Mayhar hit the fantasy scene in 1979
with several novels.
Since Mayhar has a self-admitted penchant
for using at least one unpronounceable
word in each title, we'll let her tell you
what she's written in the fantasy and
science fiction genres.
In nineteen seventy-nine,
Doubleday published
How the Gods Wolf and Kiranar.
Uh, in eighty double day brought out the
Seekers of Sarah Nun.
Eighty one brought uh Soul Singer
of Tier Note
from Athenium.
Eighty two
busted loose like a pot of popcorn.
Uh Warlock's gift came from Doubleday
in the spring.
Um paperback reprints from Ace of How the
Guys Walking Seekers of Sharon came out
that spring.
Oh
Runes of the Liar came out from Athenium
that uh
fall.
And uh
Golden Dream of the Odyssey came
out that fall.
So it it
sort of just
grabbed you up like a tornado
and carried
you away
spinning.
We asked Mayhar what type of fantasy she
writes.
It is really
more toward heroic
fantasy.
Though
not in the the sword
and sorcery ty type
of thing. These are pe
uh more
people
who
are heroic
not
through
physical
strength or anything like
that, but because of the press of
circumstance and integrity.
I try to write about the way people can be
and often are in
uh well as it is fast. I mean,
there's a place for that.
But uh
I have never seen that the
cause
of
human enlightenment
has been
forwarded
too much
by depicting
the absolute
worst aspects of
human nature.
People can be
noble,
they
can be courageous.
And they very often are, so why not write
about it?
Since she is a poet as well, we asked
Mayhar if writing poetry helps her write
prose.
I uh
talk to a lot
of college classes
and and uh
I belong to a group that has
beginners in it, and uh
I tell them write poetry even if it's bad
poetry,
because
in poetry you don't have a novel's
worth of elbow room.
You can't use twenty-five wrong
words to get across an
idea that two perfect
words will give with put, you know, with
real impact.
Uh poetry takes the laziness out of it.
It makes you search for the
proper word, the proper
phrase, the exact
construction that conveys what
what you want to give.
Mayher published her first novel after her
children left home.
We asked her if she ever wishes she had
gotten published earlier.
You know,
I have given that a lot of thought.
It's a very rough road of house
but I have come to the conclusion
that people who have a great deal of
cassette, they're young,
quite often don't
keep
pushing themselves to to refine their
technique,
get better and better and better so
that by golly, you are so good they can't
turn you down.
Besides which, you know, when you live
four years, you know a lot of things you
didn't know when you'd live twenty-five
years. You understand not only what people
do, but how they feel under different
circumstances when uh when a husband comes
home and he's lost his job.
You not only know how he acts, you know
how he and his wife feel about it.
And this is something that I think causes
a great deal of modern uh non-genre
fiction to be superficial.
People are writing about it who've never
stood in those shoes, and who don't really
understand what it does to your gut to
have a child get deathly ill at two
o'clock in the morning, you know. All
this sort of thing.
We'll have more with Artit Mayhar on our
next show.
This has been the science fiction radio
show production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the science fiction radio show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is Bill Vernon.
And Daryl Lane.
Artith Mayhar is an East Texas writer who
recently began publishing in a variety of
genres. She has written several fantasy
novels and one science fiction novel.
That being a continuation of the fuzzy
series started by the late H.
Beam Piper. Mayor's contribution to that
series is entitled Golden Dream, The Fuzzy
Odyssey. Mayhar has written some westerns
and she's working in other genres.
She manages to write a lot because she
works so rapidly.
This is amazing because she lives on a
farm and she has a lot of chores to do
each day. We asked Mayhar to describe a
typical day.
So I'm standing there washing dishes, or
I'm out there milking the cow, and I'm
listening for the postman.
You know when Snoopy is a vulture when
he's on top of his doghouse being a
vulture. That's the way I am with the
postman.
Uh I milk one of the cows and and turn the
five calves in on her and her partner and
pen feed the goats and feed the cats and
feed the dogs and
then I get the mail and look through. And
I got such interesting mail.
A lot of days I begin my real work.
Of course, in among this, I usually try to
sweep the porch and uh
uh straighten the stacks.
I've discovered you don't have to clean
your living room if you keep your stacks
straight.
So I straighten the stacks.
Then I hit the typewriter about nine
o'clock usually.
And I may answer six letters before I
start writing, but then
I will usually write depending on what I
am engaged in from
three to seven hours.
I can write
a pretty fair size short story in
two and a half, three hours.
But if I'm working on a book, then and
it's really hot, well, I'll go right on to
it till three thirty or four o'clock
sometime.
And I'm one of these lucky people I don't
have to eat.
I don't need to eat, so I don't get
hungry.
Don't have to interrupt myself.
And uh
about three thirty or four that all the
goats starts yelling out the pen.
I don't know why she yells at four
o'clock, but she usually does, and that
wakes me up, and I think, you know, I
don't know whether I can get my old bones
up from here or not.
I'd better try and see, you know, and
among much creaking groaning, I
poised myself off
steel and straighten out and uncrank the
back and
so that's then when I go out and
oh I may dig in my garden or or uh take a
walk up up our little road. I
time to get back, it's time to
lick the cat all over again and milk the
cows and put the calves on, feed the
goats, and
all that good stuff, and then it's time to
cook supper for papa, and he gets home
about
six
thirty, and so we pretty well ready to
pack it in.
So Mayhar's farm chores take up a great
deal of her day.
We wondered if she might be more
productive if she were to live in the
city.
I am a peasant to my toe name.
Uh I am not happy.
I have lived in town periodically.
And have been miserable every minute.
Oh, I had to live in Houston for sixteen
months. I thought I'd die.
We hadn't left.
Um, we've always had a little plot of
ground. Maybe maybe not with two acres,
but something we've always had some kind
of livestock.
Oh, if when spring comes, if I can't get
my hands in the dirt and make a garden,
you just better buy a straight jacket and
call the men in the white coats because
I'm ready to go off.
I do my best writing thinking in the
garden.
Or even milking the cow.
You know, the old head just keeps rolling
right along.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.